My first love was for the night sky.
كان حبي الأول لسماء الليل.
Love is complicated.
الحب معقد.
You're looking at a fly-through of the Hubble Space Telescope Ultra-Deep Field,
فأنت تنظر الى الفضاء من خلال تلسكوب هبل الفضائي الفائق العمق ،
one of the most distant images of our universe ever observed.
واحدة من أكثر الصور البعيدة لكوننا التي تمت ملاحظتها من أي وقت مضى .
Everything you see here is a galaxy,
كل ما تراه هنا هو المجرة،
comprised of billions of stars each.
التي تتألف من مليارت النجوم لكل منها .
And the farthest galaxy is a trillion, trillion kilometers away.
وأبعد مجرة عنا تبعد ترليون ترليون كيلومتر .
As an astrophysicist, I have the awesome privilege of studying
وكفزيلئية فلكية ،فلقد حظيت بهذه الدراسة الرهيبة
some of the most exotic objects in our universe.
التي تتعلق بأكثر الأجسام غرابة في كوننا .
The objects that have captivated me from first crush throughout my career
الأجسام التي فتنت بها منذ بداية مسيرتي العملية
are supermassive, hyperactive black holes.
هي اجسام ضخمة جداً ذات ثقوب سوداء حالكة السواد ،
Weighing one to 10 billion times the mass of our own sun,
تزن من 1 الى 10 أضعاف كتلة شمسنا ،
these galactic black holes are devouring material,
هذه المجرة ذات الثقوب السوداء تلتهم الأجسام،
at a rate of upwards of 1,000 times more
بمعدل أكثر من 10,000 مرة
than your "average" supermassive black hole.
من متوسط حجم ثقبك الأسود الهائل .
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
These two characteristics,
هاتين الخاصيتين ،
with a few others, make them quasars.
مع غيرهم ،جعلت منهم نجوم عملاقة وبعيدة
At the same time, the objects I study
وبنفس الوقت ،فإن الاجسام التي ادرسها
are producing some of the most powerful particle streams
تنتج بعض من أكثر تيارات الجسيمات القوية
ever observed.
التي تمت ملاحظتها من أي وقت مضى.
These narrow streams, called jets,
هذه التيارات الضيقه ،تسمى السواد الحالك،
are moving at 99.99 percent of the speed of light,
وتسير في 99.99 في المئة من سرعة الضوء،
and are pointed directly at the Earth.
ويتم تحديها بوضوح من كوكب الأرض .
These jetted, Earth-pointed, hyperactive and supermassive black holes
هذه الفوهات السوداءالعملاقة التي يمكن ملاحظتها من الأرض
are called blazars, or blazing quasars.
تسمى النجوم الزائفه المتوهجة ،أو البعيدة .
What makes blazars so special is that they're some of the universe's
وما يجعل هذه النجوم مميزة للغاية هو أنها جزء من الجسيمات
most efficient particle accelerators,
الفعالة في كوننا ،
transporting incredible amounts of energy throughout a galaxy.
نقل كميات لا تصدق من الطاقة في جميع أنحاء المجرة.
Here, I'm showing an artist's conception of a blazar.
هنا ،سأوضح تصور فني لنجم زائف .
The dinner plate by which material falls onto the black hole
لوحة عشاء حيث تسقط الجسيمات في الفوهات السوداء
is called the accretion disc,
وها ما يسمى بالقرص بالمتزايد،
shown here in blue.
ويظهر هنا باللون الأزرق.
Some of that material is slingshotted around the black hole
بعض من تلك المواد تنجذب بقوة حول الفوهات السوداء
and accelerated to insanely high speeds
وتتسارع إلى سرعات عالية بجنون
in the jet, shown here in white.
بالنجم كما هو موضح هنا باللون الأبيض.
Although the blazar system is rare,
بالرغم من أن نظام هذه النجوم أمر نادر الحدوث
the process by which nature pulls in material via a disk,
فإن العملية التي تقوم الطبيعة من خلالها بجذب هذه المواد عن طريق القرص،
and then flings some of it out via a jet, is more common.
ومن ثم فإن عملية دفع بعضها خارجاً ، من الفوهات هو الأكثر شيوعاً .
We'll eventually zoom out of the blazar system
وستكون بنهاية المطاف مصغرة من نظام النجوم
to show its approximate relationship to the larger galactic context.
لإظهار علاقتها التقريبية إلى سياق المجرة أكبر.
Beyond the cosmic accounting of what goes in to what goes out,
وبعيداً عن الحسابات الكونية لما يدخل ويخرج،
one of the hot topics in blazar astrophysics right now
واحدة من القضايا الساخنة في الفيزياء الفلكية للنجوم الزائفة الآن
is where the highest-energy jet emission comes from.
هو من أين تكمن الطاقة العليا التي تخرج منها الانبعاثات من هذه الفوهات.
In this image, I'm interested in where this white blob forms
في هذه الصورة ،أنا مهتم بتوضيح مكان تشكيل السائل الأبيض
and if, as a result, there's any relationship between the jet
واذا كان نتيجةً لذلك ،اي علاقة بين الفوهات
and the accretion disc material.
ومواد الأقراص المزودة .
Clear answers to this question
أجوبة واضحة لهذا السؤال
were almost completely inaccessible until 2008,
حيث أننا تقريباأ لم نتوصل اليها لغاية عام 2008،
when NASA launched a new telescope that better detects gamma ray light --
عندما أطلق وكالة ناسا تلسكوب جديد أفضل من الكشف عن طريق أشعة جاما --
that is, light with energies a million times higher
وهذا الضوء مع طاقاته أعلى مليون مرة
than your standard x-ray scan.
من المعيار الخاص بالمسح عن طريق الأشعة السينية.
I simultaneously compare variations between the gamma ray light data
وبنفس الوقت قمت بمقارنة الإختلافات بين بيانات ضوء أشعة جاما
and the visible light data from day to day and year to year,
وبيانات الضوء المرئي من يوم لاخر ومن سنه لأخرى،
to better localize these gamma ray blobs.
لتوطين سوائل أشعة جاما بشكل أفضل.
My research shows that in some instances,
بحثي أظهر أنه في بعض الحالات،
these blobs form much closer to the black hole
هذه السوائل تتشكل بشكل أقرب من الفوهات السوداء
than we initially thought.
مما كنا نعتقد في البداية .
As we more confidently localize
وكما قمنا بكل ثقة بتوطين
where these gamma ray blobs are forming,
المكان الذي تتشكل فيه سوائل أشعة جاما،
we can better understand how jets are being accelerated,
فأصبح من السهل أن نفهم كيف تتزايد الفوهات،
and ultimately reveal the dynamic processes
ونكشف في نهاية المطاف العمليات الديناميكية
by which some of the most fascinating objects in our universe are formed.
لأكثر الأجسام التي تتشكل بشكل مذهل في كوننا.
This all started as a love story.
كل هذا بدأ كقصة حب .
And it still is.
وما زال كذلك .
This love transformed me from a curious, stargazing young girl
هذا الحب حولني من فتاة صغيرة فضولية تحب التديق بالنجوم
to a professional astrophysicist,
الى عالمة فيزياء فلكية محترفة،
hot on the heels of celestial discovery.
مهتمه فيما يخص الاكتشافات السماوية .
Who knew that chasing after the universe
التي تعرف أن مطاردة الكون
would ground me so deeply to my mission here on Earth.
ستعلقني بشكل كبير لمهمتي هنا بالأرض .
Then again, when do we ever know where love's first flutter
ومرة أخرى ،عندما عرفنا للمرة الأولى اين يكمن الحب
will truly take us.
سيأسرنا حقاً
Thank you.
شكراً .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )